Some stuff:

Story drivers:

	A story driver is the determinate force behind your story. 
	
	Questions: How did your Main Character get involved?
		  What's keeping your characters in the story?

Examples:

	Plot Driven story:

		An overall story arc is keeping your characters in the story. You have written an idea and present your characters with scenarios they must respond to. A plot driven story can mean that, no matter how hard they try, they can't stop what's coming. The villain won't change theirminds or course of action based on what your characters do.

		Examples: The fifth Element
			      The villain of this story is a thing that wants nothing but the complete destruction of life within the universe. The characters can't stop this, so we follow their adventure to stop the oncoming cataclysm.

	Setting driven:
		
		I don't care what anyone says, your environment can drive a story. War settings, natural disasters. Like a plot driven story, your characters can't stop what's coming or what has already happened, in this case.

	The thing about settings is that there is no apparent evil or villain challenging your characters. There is no concsious behind the chaos, as it were.

		Examples: Jurassic park
			        Despite the argument that John Hammond could be seen as an idealistic villain or someone that was so wrapped up in his goals that he failed to take into consideration the "what-if" disaster scenario, the villain of this movie isn't necessarily a person despite the trigger event being initiated by a person. This is an example of the environment turning itself upside down and the characters having to race from one situation to another to stay alive.

			 2012
			         Disaster movies about natural upheval like 2012 have no villain. There is no bad guy, despite there being villain archetypes present. The natural enviornment is the thing presenting the challenges and these stories can be the thing that wakes up a character or set of characters to the realization that they are very small but it takes big ideas and a whole lot of risk taking to survive.

	Character driven:

		These are the most fun, the easiest and the ones that people can kill the fastest. All a character needs is a call-to-action and they are on the way. The protagonist and antagonist essentially take turns and plan as they go, reacting to each other and readjusting the way they achieve their goals. One side of the other doesn't necessarily need a goal to give the other a hard time. Sometimes, a villain just wants to have fun or see what someone would do and they chose the Main character as the guinea pig for their entertainment.

		These plots are often rushed and cluttered but if well organized, can be the most malleable and even be the bridge between the other drivers. A good character driven story takes its time and pushes one idea to the next without over or underwhelming the audience with information.

"puppetmaster" villains are somewhat exempt from the exchange. They are the bigger bad behind the scenes motivating lesser bads to do something or somehow influencing them or are pawns, unknowingly or otherwise, in bigger bad's plan.

this can draw on sympathy strings from the main character if found a lesser bad is being manipulated by bigger bad. This can draw on the grey regions of morality and, thus, sensing the humanity in a character.

		Examples: Harry Potter
			      There is always some sort of exchange and refocusing going on between Harry and VOldemort. When one acts, the other reacts. When challenges present either side, the adjust and overcome to the crescendo. 


Villains:

A villain can literally be anything but somtimes it's not fair to call them villains. Villain denotes evil and not all villains or evil nor are they bad. Whatever challenges the protagonist is considered, in some part, an antaognist, not matter how good or evil it is.

Say, for instance, your main character takes the low moral road on an issue. Let's say...torture.

2 characters need to gain information from a 3rd. Your main character suggests they are at an impass and time is of the essence, so, MC suggests forcing the 3rd character to listen to telletubby tracks for an hour at a time until they break. The second character, your supporting lead, says hell to the no. That's just low. They, in turn, get into an argument.

For a moment there, character 2 is antagonizing the main character.

		Types of antagonists:

			Ideas, people, places of doom, cursed objects, nature, internal conflict.

Your main character can be their own worst enemy and nothing a bigger bad can throw at them will do nearly as much damage as the demons that plague the mind of your protagonist.

Batman Begins is a great example where bruce wayne had to overcome everything he feared and all of his good intentions to become batman and face the final conflict. Which still managed to be his unspoken fears that he was still not quite over.

----------------------

Storytelling requires a lot of writing ahead and internal details and ideas. You have got to stay organized and make sure that everyone's path is clear in your mind. If you're writing a character driven plot, the personality of your character may change your mind about a situation but, you're supposed to be god. You wrote the rules of your world.

Having said that.

The god complex:

That's right. When you're writing, you are god. Your are also the devil.

You are law and you are chaos. If you write a story and there are explicit rules: Gravity need not apply here, for example, you must make sure that your characters follow that rule. even your antagonists fall prey to your rules.

If someone defies a rule or a previous dilemma, this can open plotholes and confuse your audience. If it can be justified, make sure to explain it, even if you do it later.

You'll always have someone going : What the hell happened here?!

if you were planning on covering this hole, just tell them to hold on. "You'll see."

Or in the words of... *ahem* River song "Spoliers!"

If you didn't plan to cove the hole and your audience discovers it, you'll need to adjust your rules, oh dear God of your universe.


Anyway, this is a low down dirty run down about things. Lots of things.

Story things.

I wanted to do this for you all because last time? It was an unexpected gift of exposure there and I was planning on redoing this whole thing anyway.

hurr

-Dj 